<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Praise and adoration, or, A sermon on Trinity-Sunday before the University at Oxford, 1681 by Thomas Mannyngham ...</title>
            <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1851</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12628071</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12628071</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64688</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64688)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 966:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Praise and adoration, or, A sermon on Trinity-Sunday before the University at Oxford, 1681 by Thomas Mannyngham ...</title>
                  <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CIII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64688:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64688:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRAISE and ADORATION. OR, A SERMON ON TRINITY-SUNDAY BEFORE THE Univerſity at <hi>Oxford.</hi> 1681.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS MANNYNGHAM,</hi> M. A. late Fellow of <hi>New-Colledge Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crook</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:64688:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64688:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM 103. V. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul! and all that is within me bleſs his holy Name!</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is an <hi>Habitual,</hi> and alſo an <hi>Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al praiſing</hi> or Glorifying of God: the <hi>firſt</hi> conſiſts in a regular confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of our Lives, or the general courſe of our Actions to the holy Will and Commands of God: But <hi>Actual Adoration,</hi> which is to be the Subject of my Enſuing Diſcourſe, is it ſelf a peculiar and ſolemn part of Divine Worſhip: which does not only conſiſt in an open recitation of Hymns and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Songs, but alſo in a ſilent Exultation of our Faculties, and a Religious warmth of Soul wrought by Heavenly Objects.</p>
            <p>Now there are many Words and Phraſes in holy Scripture, eſpecially in this Book of Pſalms, which are often us'd to expreſs the ſame Duty of Bleſſing or praiſing the Lord; And though they are promiſcuouſly inſerted (as certainly they ought to be, either in Popular or Poetick Writings) yet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64688:3"/>are they, many of them, of peculiar limitation and ſignificancy; which being ſomewhat ſtated and explain'd, may ſerve to eſtabliſh a full and eaſie notion of what in my following Diſcourſe I ſhall make more copious and leſs nice reflexions.</p>
            <p>Wherefore our moſt humble and worthy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, our ſincere devout reſentments of the Divine Perfections, are neceſſarily requir'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the <hi>Inviſible Adoration</hi> of the Heart, and Soul, and Spirit; which from its Vital and inward heat, is continually diſplaying it ſelf into great variety of External Evidences, according to the diverſity of thoſe objects about which it is immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant. So that we may be ſaid to <hi>praiſe</hi> the Lord, when we declare his free and moſt excellent works of Mercy and Juſtice, of Creation and Providence: to <hi>Magnifie</hi> and <hi>Adore</hi> him, when we ſet forth his incommunicable and Natural Excellencies, ſuch as his Omnipotence, Immenſity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider'd, with his Univerſal Dominion and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty over all Creatures, may ſeem to ſignifie all that we mean by the <hi>Glorious Majeſty</hi> of God. We may be ſaid to <hi>Bleſs</hi> the Lord by our wiſhes and words; and being the good we wiſh is Extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to his Nature, and not yet obtained, as, that the whole World may be converted and fear his Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we muſt be ſure to bleſs him with our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64688:3"/>
               <hi>endeavours</hi> too: But chiefly this <hi>Bleſſing</hi> is effected by our moſt <hi>ſolemn Gratulations;</hi> for ſeeing we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not confer any real good on God, we muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually expreſs our joy and gladneſs for his actual poſſeſſion of all poſſible perfection. To <hi>worſhip</hi> him, uſually denotes a moſt humble poſture of Body, when we incline towards, or proſtrate our ſelves on that Duſt out of which we were made. We <hi>Glorifie</hi> God with our Mouths; and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Pſalmiſt calls his Tongue his Glory, Awake thou my Glory. <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> is an open profeſſion and a hearty acknowledgment that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Benefit moſt freely, and without any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of our own. <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> ſeem to differ in theſe reſpects: we <hi>adore</hi> God for things that were acted long ago, which concern not us any more, than that they were the Effects of his Omnipotence, as for all the Wonders done in the behalf of the Children of <hi>Iſrael: Thanksgiving</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to thoſe Benefits which either we immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately receive, or whoſe effects are communicated to us. Alſo we <hi>adore</hi> God for his Judgments and his Vengeance, however diſplayed, either on our Enemies, or on our ſelves; for which we are not properly ſaid to return <hi>Thanksgivings;</hi> becauſe <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> reſpects the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Action, <hi>Thanksgivings</hi> the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of it. Theſe Words and Phraſes being
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64688:4"/>thus ſomewhat explain'd, I ſhall make no ſcruple to uſe them again in their popular ſenſe and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, according as I ſhall find occaſion for them, in my farther amplifications on the Text, which I will endeavour to handle in theſe <hi>three</hi> reſpects.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. You may be pleas'd to conſider the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Excellence</hi> of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adoration. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. I ſhall endeavour to ſhew what are thoſe <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties</hi> and <hi>Capacities</hi> of the Soul, whereby this <hi>Adoration</hi> is perform'd. <hi>All that is within me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. I will point out ſome of thoſe <hi>Benefits</hi> which will ariſe from a Worthy perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Duty. <hi>Bleſs the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. You may be pleas'd to conſider the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Excellence</hi> of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adoration. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Praiſes,</hi> which bear the name of all that we can properly call <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> are as well the Eternal Dictates of <hi>Nature,</hi> as the moſt Sacred Commands of <hi>Revelation;</hi> and if there may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed any remarkable precedency in theſe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64688:4"/>Duties of Natural and Reveal'd Religion, <hi>Praiſe</hi> or <hi>Adoration</hi> ſeems juſtly to challenge that Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative: for ſhould not we firſt acknowledge our Being, before we view and lament its imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? ſhould not we return our ſacrifices of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for what we have already received, before we implore the Divine Benignity for further acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, freſh ſupplies, and new aſſiſtances? Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Juſtice obliges us at all times, firſt to look back and magnifie the Lord for our actual preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, before we preſume to put up our Petitions for pardon and future ſecurity; and it requires a Pſalm of Thankſgiving, that we are in a capacity to know our Wants, to ſurvey our Infirmities. The meanneſs of our nature has indeed placed us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the poſſibility of making any Recompence, and yet the indigency of our condition ſtill calls upon us to make freſh acknowledgments: and however imperfect theſe oblations are, yet are they the only ſhew of real ſervice we can render, the only Image of Requital which our Creator has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged us.</p>
            <p>And as this Adoration is our indiſpenſable Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo 'tis our Advantage and our glory too: 'tis not only the buſineſs of our Creation, but the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of it; and we never appear in a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted State, than when we <hi>Glorifie.</hi> In the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64688:5"/>of this Duty, we more eminently make good our Communion with Saints and Angels, whilſt with thoſe bleſſed Spirits we conſtitute the ſame Choire, and make one Univerſal Hallelujah.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſurely can be more <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Natural,</hi> than to imploy our breath to the glory of him who gave it us: nothing more <hi>profitable,</hi> than to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Lord into greater Mercies to our ſelves: Nothing more <hi>delightful,</hi> than to be always full of glorious Conceptions, always pouring forth the Language of Bleſſing and Affection! <hi>Prayers</hi> are but the Mournful Draught and Table of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, the repreſentation of our Ship-wreckt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Repentance</hi> has a gloomy ſide; but <hi>Praiſe</hi> is Faiths and Reaſons Triumph, a bright, unmixt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate Joy, and only wants ſome few degrees of being all we can conceive of Heaven. Therefore</p>
            <p n="2">II. You may be pleas'd to conſider what are thoſe Faculties and Capacities of the Soul whereby this Duty is perform'd.</p>
            <p>Now the powers of the Soul which are more eminently concern'd in the <hi>Acts</hi> of Adoration, ſeem to be <hi>theſe Three.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Our Reaſon.</item>
                  <item>2. Our Imagination.</item>
                  <item>3. Our Affections.</item>
               </list>For we may be ſaid to Praiſe the Lord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64688:5"/>with our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in theſe two reſpects. 1. When it perfectly and freely ſubmits to the <hi>High My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> or the Doctrines of <hi>pure Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 2. When it humbly and devoutly buſies it ſelf about the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Attributes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the Works of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Providence;</hi> and though they are objects of Revelation too, yet have they a ſure foundation in <hi>Right Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> and therefore may ſafely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a <hi>modeſt</hi> and <hi>affectionate</hi> enquiry. We may be ſaid to praiſe the Lord with our <hi>Imagination,</hi> when we ſtudy to adorn our Divine Conceptions with the moſt <hi>Excellent Idea's,</hi> with the moſt <hi>lively Repreſentations</hi> we can invent.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, We may be ſaid to Praiſe the Lord with our <hi>Affections,</hi> when the whole Duty is perform'd with ſtrong vehemency of Soul, and intenſeneſs of Spirit, with the Unions of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Wonder,</hi> and ſuch like bright Affections as perfect and exalt our moſt Spiritual performances. Of theſe in their Order.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may be ſaid to Praiſe the Lord with our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> when it perfectly and freely ſubmits it ſelf to the High Myſteries of <hi>Faith,</hi> or the Doctrines of <hi>pure Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it not an eſpecial Excellency of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, that as all its Precepts for <hi>Life</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64688:6"/>
               <hi>Manners</hi> are ſo perſpicuouſly deliver'd, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly agreeable to the beſt conceptions of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that the <hi>humble</hi> Perſon cannot miſtake his way to Heaven; ſo alſo there are ſuch Hights and Depths in the receſſes of our <hi>Faith,</hi> as perhaps the Seraphims cannot comprehend? And although theſe Propoſitions of our <hi>Belief</hi> alſo be as <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>Evident</hi> as Hiſtory and Language can make them; as infallibly <hi>true</hi> and <hi>certain</hi> as that God who has reveal'd them; yet even in our modeſt contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations on them, the exceſſive glory of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is apt to ſtrike back, and ſcatter our Natural light into the Confuſions of Broken Knowledge and Admiration; into Humility, Love, Praiſe and Reſignation; thus <hi>perfecting</hi> our Natures, whilſt it confounds our Enquiries! So that the moſt <hi>Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Myſteries</hi> of Chriſtianity, how Incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoever in their <hi>Intrinſic Natures,</hi> are yet as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable and conducive to the Ends of Religion, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the promoting <hi>true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> as the moſt practical and familiar Doctrines and encouragements of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Were indeed our <hi>Myſteries</hi> like thoſe of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Heathen, whoſe <hi>Adyta</hi> and <hi>Penetralia</hi> were but ſo many Cloyſters of Separated Impurity, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Concealments of Spiritual Craft, or of Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Appropriated Luſt; then the nice exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64688:6"/>World might very well complain of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures of Prieſts, of the abſurdities of a Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Faith: but when the <hi>Myſteries</hi> we pretend to, are not ſuch as are made ſo by Shrines, Temple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>characters, and a Traditionary Caution; but ſuch as are expos'd to the promiſcuous, yet humble view of all men, in <hi>Confeſſions, Creeds,</hi> and <hi>Catechiſms;</hi> and being thus expos'd, they are no <hi>Incongruities</hi> to our <hi>Moral conceptions,</hi> as moſt of the Heathen's were; nor yet <hi>Contradictions</hi> to our <hi>Natural Reaſoning,</hi> as ſome would have them; (for they are not ſuch objects as lye within its Sphere, or within the reach of its common Axioms) but are rather ſo many Humiliations of our Underſtandings, ſo many Gracious Affrightments, and incomprehenſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearments of our Souls unto <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> So that if the thoughts of a <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>Unity,</hi> and a <hi>Unity</hi> in <hi>Trinity,</hi> amaze thy mind, thou may'ſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently relieve thy ſelf with this contemplation, That all this Unconceivable Diſtinction of <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtences</hi> extends it ſelf to thy Benefit and Comfort, to reach thee out of Perdition and thy Primitive Curſe! that all this Ineffable <hi>oeconomy</hi> of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is thy Redemption, thy Sanctification, in a Word, thy <hi>Multiply'd Salvation!</hi> And conſidering likewiſe, that on one ſide we have the expreſs De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of Holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> the Definitions of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64688:7"/>Councils, the Writings and Devotions of Primitive <hi>Fathers,</hi> the Blood and Conſciences of Holy <hi>Martyrs,</hi> to teſtifie and ſeal their early <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> their Venerable <hi>Certainty,</hi> and moſt faithful <hi>Conveyance;</hi> and then on the other ſide, that there is nothing but Scholaſtick <hi>Subtilty,</hi> and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> to <hi>Weaken</hi> or <hi>Corrupt</hi> them; bold <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> malicious <hi>Cavilling,</hi> and impious <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> to <hi>oppoſe</hi> them; I ſay, conſidering all theſe things, what poſſibly can deter any <hi>good</hi> and <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> man, even in this perverſe diſputing Age, from triumphantly embracing the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of Faith with a ſtrong and heroical Aſſent, with a noble captivity of Mind, and the moſt vigorous <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Adoration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Happy had it been for the Chriſtian World, if theſe <hi>Eminencies</hi> in Religion had been always guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a Flaming Cherubim, and been only made the illuſtrious Themes of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!</hi> But now, alas! the Controverſies of the Church about theſe higher points, will hardly ſuffer us to ſpeak <hi>Devotionally</hi> of our Myſteries! <hi>Grammatical</hi> ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceties, and <hi>Socinian</hi> figures, have weaken'd the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Reverence of many Texts! Every <hi>Dutch Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteme</hi> is arrogantly big with the bold Explications of the Myſterious <hi>Trinity,</hi> and of thoſe heights and depths before which the very Angels tremble and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64688:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>vail! What if ſome holy Perſons of old, perhaps of more Piety and devout Affections, than Learning and Phyloſophy, were admitted (like <hi>Moſes</hi> into the Cloud) humbly to converſe with God about this Dreadful <hi>Myſtery,</hi> to be a Bank and a Mound againſt an eager and impetuous <hi>Hereſie</hi> then ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in the Church, and to be a ſtanding Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt all future ſwellings of proud Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet there is no reaſon but that there ſhould be ſome reſtraint alſo about <hi>this Mountain</hi> too, to fence off the Multitude and Common Beaſts, and to keep the Viler Herd at awful diſtance, leſt they break through unto the Lord, to gaze and periſh! <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may be ſaid to <hi>Praiſe</hi> the Lord with our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> when it humbly and devoutly buſies it ſelf about the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Attributes</hi> of God manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Works of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Providence;</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are Objects of Divine Revelation too, yet have they a ſure foundation in <hi>Right Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> and therefore may ſafely admit of a modeſt and affectionate enquiry. <hi>Bleſs his holy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where, by the <hi>Name</hi> of God is meant all that we are able to conceive of his <hi>Perfections,</hi> his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>Attributes;</hi> and thoſe not as they are <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſically</hi> handled, and jejunely mingled with the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64688:8"/>
               <hi>Definitions</hi> of the Schools, but as they are moſt <hi>pathetically</hi> ſet forth in <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous <hi>works,</hi> and <hi>gracious diſpenſations</hi> to Mankind.</p>
            <p>Alas! it is not the dry Skeleton of dead and ſhapeleſs Reaſon, or the Scholaſtick joynting of prodigious Terms, (which repreſent an Image rather <hi>Gaſtly</hi> than <hi>Admirable</hi>) that can excite and animate our <hi>Gratulations</hi> and our <hi>Praiſes;</hi> but there muſt be the Life and Features, and all the <hi>Moving Elegance</hi> of the Frame, to give us bright concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of its Dignity. And therefore we find that <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> ſcarce ever meddles with an <hi>Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute</hi> in its <hi>Abſolute</hi> Nature, but only in a <hi>Relative</hi> and endearing way; and that <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> (which are richly pregnant with all thoſe <hi>Divine Perfections</hi> which moſt nearly concern us) are the two choſen and moſt ſublime Topi's on which the <hi>Euchariſtical Pſalms</hi> are chiefly ſpent.</p>
            <p>And who among us can forbear from breaking forth into acts of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adoration,</hi> when he conſiders how the Almighty was pleas'd out of his Infinite and Boundleſs <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> according to the <hi>Freedom</hi> of his Eternal Decree, I muſt not ſay to <hi>Empty,</hi> but to <hi>Irradiate</hi> himſelf into this ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing variety of Beings, this ſtupendous Fabrick of the World, indefinite to our moſt Travelling <hi>Conceptions,</hi> and only <hi>leſs infinite</hi> than <hi>He</hi> who made
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64688:8"/>it? <hi>Here we may behold his</hi> Wiſdom <hi>in its Throne, and praiſe him in the Firmament of his Power! whilſt we attentively recall how by his Word the Heavens were made, and all the Hoſt of them by the breath of his Mouth! how he ſpread out the Sky like a Molten Glaſs, and ordered the ballancings of the Clouds! how he ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the North o'er the empty Place, and hung the Earth upon nothing!</hi> how he form'd the firſt Man out of the Duſt of the Ground, breath'd into his Noſtrils the immortal <hi>Halitus,</hi> or Breath of Life, and made that laſt Imperial Draught to ſtand the <hi>Beauty,</hi> the <hi>Dominion,</hi> and the <hi>Sabbath</hi> of all his wondrous Works! in a Word, how raviſhing a Reflection muſt the <hi>Creation</hi> needs be to Men and Angels too, when <hi>God Almighty</hi> is Repreſented in the <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> as it were <hi>ſitting down,</hi> Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating, and with all intellectual Complacency ſurveying the <hi>Accompliſh'd Miracle!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, as for <hi>Providence,</hi> what fuller matter for our <hi>Celebrations</hi> have we, than to conſider, how all the unaccountable Paſſages here below, which ſeem ſo rugged, and like wild Contingencies to us, are notwithſtanding particularly directed by the certain guidance of an <hi>Almighty Wiſdom,</hi> and in their proper ſeaſons produc'd by a Beautiful Order of Cauſes! that not only <hi>Univerſal Nature,</hi> but <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Cities, Private perſons,</hi> their <hi>Policies, Juſtice, Thoughts</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64688:9"/>and <hi>Contrivances,</hi> are evermore <hi>Actuated, Advanced,</hi> or <hi>Confounded,</hi> by the imperceptible ſtreams of a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Prerogative!</hi> And that all that multitude of ſtrange Appearances, which look like ſo many Monſtrous and Extravagant <hi>Lines</hi> to us in <hi>this poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> will one day be reflected into a <hi>Regular piece,</hi> and make a glorious Figure in the Beatific Viſion!</p>
            <p>I cannot well conceive how the <hi>Epicurean</hi> could ever be thought effectually to <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> the <hi>Deity,</hi> only for the bare <hi>Excellency</hi> of his <hi>Being;</hi> whom he fancied to be like ſome <hi>Perſian</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, Moroſely Great, full of himſelf, and his one Solitude, of a Cloyſter'd Majeſty, or a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> that never ſtoopt below the Heavens; whereas the <hi>Stoic</hi> more truly tells us, <hi>Nulla Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas ſine Bonitate;</hi> and we are ſufficiently ſatisfy'd that there was nothing ſo powerful to awaken <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> and reconcile men to the Sacrifices of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as that <hi>Tranſcendent goodneſs</hi> and <hi>particular Care</hi> which men evidently found to flow from what they Worſhip'd. I grant the <hi>Sun,</hi> by reaſon of its <hi>bright Appearance</hi> and reſplendency, will na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally excite a Tranſient <hi>Wonder</hi> in Beholders; but yet I queſtion whether ever it would have been <hi>Ador'd,</hi> (as it certainly was by the greateſt part of the Heathen World) and have had its <hi>own Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe</hi> offer'd it again, if it had not been for that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64688:9"/>and Experienc'd <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Benefits,</hi> which its continual Influences Hatch, produce, and perfect, for the Generations of Men.</p>
            <p>What weighty ingredients, and commanding Subjects of <hi>Adoration,</hi> were the Extraordinary Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagements of <hi>Providence</hi> in behalf of the <hi>Jews</hi> and their Religion! And accordingly we find the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Pſalmiſt</hi> every where paraphraſing on thoſe great and numerous <hi>Miracles</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> and the <hi>Deſart,</hi> in an exceeding ſublimity of Phraſe, in all the Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of <hi>Eaſtern Poeſie!</hi> and here might be one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon given why the <hi>Inanimate Creation</hi> is ſo <hi>diſtinctly</hi> call'd upon in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> to <hi>Praiſe</hi> the Lord; becauſe ſo many of thoſe Beings had ſtarted from their <hi>own Law</hi> and <hi>Natures,</hi> to be either an Eminent <hi>reſcue,</hi> or a mighty <hi>Conduct</hi> to the Choſen people; that in the <hi>Jewiſh oeconomy</hi> it is hard to determine, whether greater <hi>Miracles</hi> were perform'd by the Miniſtry of the <hi>Elements,</hi> or of the appointed <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We may be ſaid to praiſe the Lord with our <hi>Imagination,</hi> when we ſtudy to adorn our <hi>Divine Conceptions</hi> with the moſt <hi>Excellent Idea's,</hi> with the moſt <hi>lively Repreſentations</hi> we can invent: for not only Reaſon and Judgment, but alſo Imagination and Fancy; not only the <hi>Firmament,</hi> but even the <hi>Meteors</hi> too, are call'd upon to <hi>praiſe</hi> the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64688:10"/>
            <p>The <hi>Imagination</hi> is the chief Spring and Engine of our <hi>Affections;</hi> it gives Sublimity, Spirit, and Vivacity to our <hi>Conceptions,</hi> Beauty and colour to our <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> and communicates all thoſe agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Illuſtrations</hi> which ſerve to adorn the <hi>ſeverity</hi> of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> The exacteſt <hi>Science</hi> we are acquainted with, cannot ſupply us with ſuch cautious forms of Speech, but that they are full of Soleciſm, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely defective and inadequate, when apply'd to Notions concerning <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Heaven:</hi> The moſt accurate <hi>wiſdom</hi> of Words that can be invented, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not defend it ſelf from many <hi>Abſurdities,</hi> when <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively</hi> converſant about an <hi>Infinite Object,</hi> and which cannot be fully comprehended; becauſe in ſuch a caſe there is a greater Latitude of ſtill ſhewing what a thing <hi>is not,</hi> than what <hi>it is.</hi> But then what we want of ſtrict <hi>ſcientifical propriety</hi> in our Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes concerning <hi>Divine</hi> ſubjects, may be nobly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd by rais'd and <hi>figurative adumbrations:</hi> And this is wholly the buſineſs of the <hi>Imagination;</hi> which, when it has warily receiv'd the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> of its Object from a <hi>ſuperiour faculty,</hi> may be allow'd to raiſe the Mind into a nobler Amplitude of thought, and to kindle it into vaſter Conceptions; and then to beautifie and ſet them forth with all thoſe proper Ornaments which uſually recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a <hi>ſpeculation</hi> to our <hi>Affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:64688:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fancy,</hi> indeed, is not permitted to give a Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and <hi>definitive</hi> ſentence, or to cloſe up its Period with an <hi>Anathema;</hi> but it may ſearch for <hi>lively Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations:</hi> For ſuch <hi>ſimilitudes</hi> of things as may beſt ſuit with the <hi>Analogy</hi> of our <hi>Natures;</hi> alſo for ſuch tranſcendent and <hi>ſuperlative Terms,</hi> as are moſt apt to inflame the Soul, and to <hi>ſhadow</hi> to us the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>ſecreſie</hi> of <hi>Myſterious Truth.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> has every where exhibited to us its <hi>heavenly Wiſdom</hi> in <hi>Parables,</hi> and <hi>ſenſible Types;</hi> and proportion'd its <hi>Revelations</hi> mores to the <hi>Imaginations</hi> of Men, than to their more <hi>ſubtile</hi> modes of <hi>Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Therefore alſo God appeared to <hi>Moſes</hi> in a <hi>Cloud,</hi> and his Glory ſhone through a <hi>Veil;</hi> that ſince the <hi>Prophet</hi> was not able to ſuſtain his more <hi>open Appearance,</hi> he might with ſafety underſtand his <hi>Infinity</hi> by the <hi>concealment</hi> of an <hi>indefinite</hi> and <hi>myſterious</hi> Declaration; and more ardently deſire a further Manifeſtation of thoſe <hi>Excellencies,</hi> which were but imperfectly revealed to him in remote and diſtant Scenes: for no man ſeem'd more acquainted with God than <hi>Moſes,</hi> and no man ſeem'd more importunate to know him better: <hi>I beſeech thee ſhew me thy Glory,</hi> Exod. 33.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Similitudes</hi> and <hi>Metaphors</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> are thoſe <hi>Clouds</hi> of <hi>Incenſe</hi> wherewith at the ſame time we both <hi>enter</hi> and <hi>obſcure</hi> the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum:</hi> We
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64688:11"/>receive thoſe ſenſible Repreſentations, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Condeſcentions which God hath been pleas'd to make us of his own <hi>Nature</hi> and the <hi>other World,</hi> in the ſame manner as the Diſciples did the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of our Saviour going to <hi>Emmaus:</hi> we have not a full <hi>comprehenſion</hi> of what is thus <hi>Figur'd</hi> to us; but yet we are religiouſly affected, we have a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Senſation</hi> of its unutterable import, and our hearts <hi>burn</hi> within us.</p>
            <p>The Strength and Vehemency of the <hi>Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> will ſometimes carry forth the <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to make <hi>new Diſcoveries;</hi> 'twill excite them to take ſuch Circuits and Travels in the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Eternal Beings,</hi> till the Soul is ready to <hi>ſwim</hi> and grow giddy, and the <hi>ſpeculation</hi> turns almoſt <hi>Apoplexy;</hi> it will ſometimes actuate the mind to a ſtretch and emanation beyond its <hi>preſent Order,</hi> to a taſte and immature anticipation of <hi>unproportion'd Knowledge:</hi> And this does not proceed from the heat and elevation of contemplative and <hi>ſplenetick</hi> Heads, but it is the ſober atteſtation and examin'd experience of more fix'd and ſolid Brains.</p>
            <p>It is reported of a <hi>Metaphyſical Divine</hi> of our own <hi>Church,</hi> that by a long aſſiduity of thinking and a conſtant ardour of Meditation, he could ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times refine and ſublimate a Theorem to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, till it became too nice even for his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64688:11"/>when he had abated of that <hi>Temper</hi> in which he firſt fram'd it; that when the <hi>intellectual fire</hi> was out, and his Brain was ſunk into its ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary dimenſions, he could not juſtifie that ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his cooler review, which he was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain had an exact conformity to his more rais'd Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</p>
            <p>However, we need not fear any <hi>Illuſion,</hi> any <hi>Phanaticiſm</hi> from the <hi>innocent</hi> Exceſſes of the <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> whilſt they are only made the <hi>private</hi> Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an <hi>Holy Life;</hi> whilſt they only promote our <hi>Adorations,</hi> not determine our <hi>Opinions;</hi> whilſt they only enter our <hi>Cloſet-Devotions,</hi> not our <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Services,</hi> or <hi>Creeds.</hi> It being alſo eaſie to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh by the <hi>concomitance</hi> or <hi>abſence</hi> of <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> when our minds are gently fill'd with <hi>Divine Images,</hi> or when they are Enthuſiaſtically <hi>poſſeſs'd</hi> with <hi>preſumptuous Enquiries.</hi> And thus the <hi>Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the meaneſt and moſt trivial faculty of the <hi>Humane Soul,</hi> under a good management may be an admirable Inſtrument and incentive of <hi>Divine Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adoration;</hi> even as God Almighty thought fit to chuſe the <hi>Rainbow,</hi> that Circle of phantaſtic colours, for the Symbole and <hi>Sacrament</hi> of his Beloved Attribute, his <hi>Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3ly.</hi> We may be ſaid to <hi>Praiſe</hi> the Lord with our <hi>Affections,</hi> when our <hi>Adoration</hi> is perform'd with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64688:12"/>ſtrong vehemency of Soul, and intenſeneſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with the Unions of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Wonder,</hi> and ſuch-like Bright Affections, as <hi>perfect</hi> and exalt our moſt <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Duties.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Will</hi> is alſo comprehended in the <hi>Affections:</hi> For as the Common <hi>Paſſions</hi> in their worſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation are the Deformities and Turbulencies of the <hi>Animal Nature;</hi> ſo the <hi>Affections</hi> are only the freſher gales of <hi>Virtue;</hi> the more <hi>enliven'd</hi> Acts of the Rational and Superiour <hi>Will:</hi> and as the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> raiſe commotions and irregularities in the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Humours</hi> of the <hi>Body;</hi> ſo theſe <hi>latter</hi> invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorate the <hi>Faculties</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> making them <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical</hi> and <hi>Divine</hi> in their Emanations.</p>
            <p>Now as the capacity of the <hi>Intellect</hi> is much lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than that of the <hi>Senſes,</hi> ſo the amplitude of the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> far ſurpaſſes that of the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding;</hi> and therefore God has requir'd that our <hi>Deſire</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of him ſhould be more <hi>perfect</hi> and complete than our <hi>Knowledge</hi> of him: for we are bound to entertain his <hi>Perfections</hi> with the <hi>clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt adheſion</hi> of <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> though we can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them onely with a <hi>Partial</hi> and enigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let men therefore boaſt of their Mighty <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings,</hi> their cloſe <hi>Deductions,</hi> their ſtrong link'd <hi>Conſequences,</hi> and their elaborate <hi>Demonſtrations</hi> in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64688:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Religion;</hi> when they have done all to juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a <hi>cautious advance</hi> towards Heaven, they will find that the <hi>Beſt Divinity</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Wonder;</hi> and that there are ſuch <hi>enlargements</hi> of the Soul ariſing from theſe <hi>Affections,</hi> as none can ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, none can conceive, but thoſe who have lain under the <hi>Bleſſed Experience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. I will endeavour to point out ſome of thoſe <hi>Benefits</hi> which will ariſe from a worthy perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Duty.</p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Holy Exerciſe</hi> being worthily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, will exalt our <hi>Faith</hi> beyond the reach of <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> or <hi>Prophaneneſs;</hi> 'twill eſtabliſh in us a <hi>permanent</hi> love to Goodneſs, and a temper of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy to the contradictions and contumelies of Vice; 'twill convey our fervent Meditations to ſuch ſafe and peaceful Heights, till the falſe Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the World make no Impreſſion on us, and its keeneſt Temptations are out-diſtanc't: It will ſecure all the ſtages of an holy Life, and reduce that Barbarous, Warlike, Stubborn, and Malicious <hi>Religion,</hi> which is now in Vogue, to the truly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Primitive <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> to a cheerful and ſerene Principle of Meekneſs, Humility, conſtant Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Univerſal Love.</p>
            <p>When the Soul is made <hi>tender</hi> with this <hi>Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Converſe,</hi> made apt to <hi>kindle</hi> at every repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64688:13"/>of Divine <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> to meet and embrace with every <hi>attribute;</hi> how vile and loath ſome muſt the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> needs appear? The very <hi>Tranſports</hi> of <hi>Adoration,</hi> whilſt they continue upon us, are a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preſervative againſt the Encroachments of Vice; and when the <hi>Holy Agitation</hi> is ceas'd, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſettles into a <hi>lively calm</hi> of laſting <hi>Gratitude</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſpeak more <hi>particularly, Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> are actions <hi>perfective</hi> of thoſe very <hi>Faculties</hi> which perform them.</p>
            <p>For, they give a Divine Brightneſs to our <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> free it from the illuſions of <hi>Sence</hi> and <hi>Paſſion,</hi> fix it on uſeful enquiries, and in all its Diſcoveries make it ſerviceable to the <hi>Sanctuary:</hi> for not onely <hi>Religious,</hi> but even <hi>Natural</hi> objects may be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plated and examin'd by the <hi>humble Adorer</hi> into My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious ſubjects of <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Wonder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The True <hi>Chriſtian Philoſopher,</hi> even from his common obſervations in ſecular Learning, will by a due <hi>Analyſis</hi> of Meditation open to himſelf a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious proſpect of Heavenly Glories; purſue every <hi>Motion</hi> and <hi>Effect</hi> to its firſt <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Author,</hi> till he finds his <hi>Scale</hi> of <hi>Contemplation</hi> to look like <hi>Jacobs Ladder,</hi> with Angels aſcending and deſcending: whilſt the proud Enquiring <hi>Naturaliſt,</hi> who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices more to his <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> than his <hi>God,</hi> will reap
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64688:13"/>nothing but Preſumption and Contempt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from his Converſation even with the <hi>Divineſt</hi> Objects. He will call a True <hi>Miracle</hi> the <hi>Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riancy</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> an Extraordinary Act of <hi>Providence</hi> onely the <hi>ſudden eruption</hi> of a <hi>Natural,</hi> though hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cauſe; or at leaſt he will debaſe theſe <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Operations</hi> of the Almighty to ſome cheap piece of <hi>Motion</hi> and <hi>Mechaniſm,</hi> that may ſerve to eaſe and pacifie his Wonder; thus looſing the improvement of his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> by the Arrogancy of his <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Invention!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This exalted Exerciſe of <hi>Praiſing</hi> and Bleſſing the Lord, will alſo fill the <hi>Imagination</hi> with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Imagery.</hi> 'Twill adorn it with the Vine and Pomgranate of the <hi>Temple,</hi> making that <hi>Faculty</hi> an holy Receptacle of pious <hi>Emblems,</hi> which in its Corrupt Nature is the chief Seat and Empire of <hi>Original Sin;</hi> the Infernal Theatre, where all the buſieſt Scenes of <hi>Temptation</hi> are diſplay'd. 'Twill teach us not to lay out our beſt ſuperlative words on Earthly things; not to embalm Rottenneſs and Corruption with the Epithites of Divinity; not to Deifie the Ambitious with ſacred Oratory, or to commit Idolatry with a too Bounteous Invention; but to reſerve a peculiar <hi>Hierarchy of Language</hi> for our Superior Intercourſe.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64688:14"/>
            <p>Laſtly, It will ſpiritualize our <hi>Affections,</hi> call them off from the defilements of the World, make them languiſh in unaccountable Unions, and give them a tender Sympathy with all the Endearments of the <hi>Canticles:</hi> It will create in us ſuch an <hi>Habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> Indulgence towards the <hi>ſweetneſſes</hi> of a Religious life, that amidſt the Avocations of the world, the diſturbances of ſecular buſineſs, and the <hi>Afflictions</hi> of <hi>Common Converſation,</hi> we ſhall be able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a <hi>ſecret Under-current</hi> of pious Aſpirations and Affections.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore ſummon up all that is <hi>within us,</hi> all the <hi>Faculties</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> of our Souls to <hi>Bleſs</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> the Lord with fervent Gratulations! For ſurely, Chriſtianity is not only a <hi>bare Avoydance</hi> of Evil, a plauſible courſe in <hi>Moral</hi> Actions, or an External living up to the <hi>Decency</hi> of a <hi>Station,</hi> (which yet in a Degenerate Age are no mean Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns and Examples) but certainly there are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd ſome <hi>Affectionate Heats,</hi> ſome Breathings and Pantings after further degrees of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and an <hi>Indefinite Perfection.</hi> And though the <hi>cold Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> are apt to call this a <hi>Spiritual Romance,</hi> and the effect of a Religious <hi>Spleen;</hi> yet we know of what <hi>Complexion</hi> they were, who ſtyl'd the <hi>miraculous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, Drunkenneſs,</hi> and the fumes of <hi>New Wine; St. Pauls Learning,</hi> and the Sobriety of his Reaſon, <hi>Madneſs</hi> and <hi>Diſtraction.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64688:14"/>
            <p>Surely, no man can be an <hi>Heretick</hi> in his <hi>ſecret Communions</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> or a dangerous <hi>Enthuſiaſt</hi> in his <hi>Inward Adorations:</hi> And if ſome <hi>Weakneſſes</hi> have been found among the <hi>private Ardours</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd;</hi> alas! what are they, but the glorious <hi>Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of the <hi>Pathetic</hi> Soul, the Noble <hi>Extravagancies</hi> of a <hi>Seraphick</hi> Temper, and an impetuous Devotion!</p>
            <p>I know there is a <hi>lower Draught</hi> of Chriſtianity; but I ſpeak a <hi>practical Myſtery</hi> to the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> to the <hi>Perfect,</hi> to the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Sons</hi> of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> who know how to be warm and affectionate in Religion, without being <hi>Superſtitious;</hi> how to <hi>Adore,</hi> without being <hi>Idolatrous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſpeak to <hi>you,</hi> who are plac'd in all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of an <hi>Extatick life;</hi> who are ſo nearly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>intelligible</hi> World, that what is but plain <hi>Picture</hi> to the Vulgar, is <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> to <hi>you;</hi> they muſt be contented with the bare <hi>Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> View, whilſt <hi>you</hi> enrich your minds with the more Excellent <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Myſtery:</hi> To <hi>you,</hi> who are able to compoſe and conſecrate the Recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your <hi>Daily Studies</hi> into an <hi>Evening Hymn;</hi> whoſe <hi>conſtant</hi> Imployment conſiſts in ſuch an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency</hi> of Spiritual Duties, as others faintly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in ſeldom Feſtivals with ſecular Mixtures and divided Powers. To <hi>you,</hi> laſtly, who are perpetually attending on the Altar; who love to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64688:15"/>ſpeak of the Glory of Gods Kingdom, and to talk of his Power; who are continually ſtanding before the Throne, having your lives hid with Chriſt in God, in Internal Joy, and the ſecrecies of an Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible peace; who live under ſuch an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſenſe of the Divine <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> that <hi>you</hi> find it difficult to refrain from publiſhing his Perfections continually, and from letting the Miſtaken world know, that it is our <hi>Priviledge,</hi> our <hi>Duty,</hi> and our <hi>Excellency,</hi> never to ceaſe from uttering in <hi>ſome meaſure</hi> our <hi>Gratulations</hi> and <hi>Praiſes</hi> here on Earth, till they Expire into <hi>Greater;</hi> till we arrive to thoſe <hi>Perfect Harmonies</hi> above, where our <hi>Glorify'd Souls</hi> and <hi>Bodies</hi> ſhall for ever dwell in an <hi>Eternal Triumph</hi> of <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Amazement!</hi> where, like the voice of Trumpets of Thunders, and like the noiſe of many Waters, vve ſhall for ever ſing <hi>Hallelujah;</hi> Salvation, and Glory, and Honour, and Power be to the <hi>Bleſſed Trinity:</hi> And again we ſhall ſing <hi>Hallelujah!</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64688:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
